A Guide to the August Dietz Civil War Collection, 1862-1909
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
August Dietz Civil War Collection, 1862-1909
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2010-069
0.4 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 folder
The August Dietz Civil War Collection contains materials originally collected by August Dietz, Richmond, VA, philatelist and printer. The collection contains single editions of Civil War-era newspapers, photographs, a woodcut and prints, quartermaster records, playing cards, a handwritten memoir, correspondence, and reproductions of stamps from the Civil War.
Dietz, August, 1869-1963
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The August Dietz Civil War Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2010.
Biographical Note
August Dietz, born in Germany in 1867, came to the United States in 1871 with his family and settled in Richmond, Virginia. In 1883, he took his first printing job and eventually took an apprenticeship at Andrews and Baptist of Richmond, considered "the art printers of the South." It was here that Dietz learned about printing and Confederate philtely, which Frank Baptist had been involved with during the Civil War. Dietz founded the Dietz Printing Company in 1900. He was a lifelong master printer and leading philatelist.
Dietz authored mnay publications, including The Postal Service of the Confederate states of America (1929), The Dietz Confederate States Catalog and Handbook (1931), and The Confederate States Post-Office Department: Its Stamps and Stationary; A record of Achievement (1950).
Dietz died in 1963 in Richmond. He is known as the "father of Confederate philately."
Scope and Content Note
The August Dietz Civil War Collection contains materials originally collected by August Dietz, Richmond, VA, philatelist and printer. The collection contains single editions of Civil War-era newspapers, photographs, a woodcut and prints, quartermaster records, playing cards, a handwritten memoir, correspondence, and reproductions of stamps from the Civil War.
The newspapers, largely from Richmond, date from the 1860s. The handwritten memoir of Colonel William McComb details the Civil War record of the 14th Tennessee Infantry. It describes the formation of the Regiment and battle descriptions through the Civil War. Along with the memoir, the collection contains two letters in regards to helping Jefferson Davis re-establish himself after the Civil War, one written by General Robert E. Lee; Confederate War Bonds; the 1862 Muster Roll of the 21st Regiment of Illinois Volunteers; and the Quartermaster Reports from Fort Wood, NY, in March 1866.
Artifacts include an woodcut, playing cards, a souvenir bookmark from the 1896 Confederate Reunion, and a commemorative medal of Lincoln's centenary. The photographs were taken at post-war Confederate Veteran reunions and other images portray Lincoln, Davis, Booth and others.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into 4 series based on material type. Series I: Newspapers, contains single editions of several southern newspapers, as well as clippings relating to JEB Stuart. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series II: Manuscripts, contains several original Confederate documents, including the handwritten memoir of General William McComb, a war bond, and quartermaster records. This series is arranged in chronological order, with undated materials at the end.
Series III: Images, contains photographs from Conferedate reunions, prints of various war-era figures, and prints created from a woodblock (located in Series IV). This series is arranged by material type.
Series IV: Artifacts, includes several items of Civil War memorabilia, including reproductions of stamps, playing cards with Confederate figures on them, and a commemorative medal of Lincoln's Centenary. This series is arranged chronologically, with undated materials at the end.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items have been removed from the collection and are available in Rare Book Room in Special Collections:
A Memorial of the 6th Annual Reunion of the United Confederate Veteran Association and the laying of the Cornerstone of the Jefferson Davis Monument, 1896
Confederate War Journal (Vol 1 Nos 1-3, 6-11)
Offical Guide to the Confederate Government 1861-1865 at Richmond
The Constitution of the United States; also, a document entitled "The Constitution of the Confederate States," arranged in parallel columns, with the differences indicated, for convenient reference and comparison, 1862.
Stonewall's Song-Book, n.d.
The Battle Record of the American Rebellion, 1860-1862.
Index Terms
Local Subjects:
Civil War
Contents List
- Series I: Newspapers, 1862-1868, n.d.
  - Civil War Newspapers, 1862-1868. (Oversize 1)
  - Jeb Stuart Clippings. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Series II: Manuscripts, 1865
  - Muster Roll 21st Regiment Illinois Volunteers, 1862. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - N.Y. Harbor Quartermaster Records, 1865-1866. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Confederate War Bond, 1862. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Confederate's Oath of Allegiance, 1865. (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence Regarding Jefferson Davis, 1869. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - William McComb's Memoir. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - August Dietz Biography. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - "Blue and Grey" Poem. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - "The Confederate Souvenir" Pamphlet. (Box-folder 1-6)
- Series III: Images, n.d.
  - Woodcut print, 1862. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Confederate Reunion Photos. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Prints of Famous Civil War-Era Figures. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Series IV: Artifacts.
  - Souvenir of the Sixth Annual Reunion U.C.V., 1896. (Box 2)
  - Commemorative Medal of the Centenary of Abraham Lincoln, 1909. (Box 2)
  - Woodblock. (Box 2)
  - Confederate Playing Cards. (Box 2)
  - The Postage Stamps of the Confederate States of America. (Box 2)